<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian confession of the late moste noble and mightie prince, Friderich of that name the third, Count Palatine by [ye] Rhein, one of the electours of the holy Empire, and Duke in Bauire: wherein constantlie and meekelie he departed out of this world the 26. of October in the yere of our Lord God 1576. Taken word for word out of his last will and testament. Whereunto is added the Lantgraue his answere to the French King</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1620-07-01</title>
            <author>Friedrich III, Elector Palatine, 1515-1576.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01236</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116026</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851243</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851243</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16513</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01236)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16513)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 509:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian confession of the late moste noble and mightie prince, Friderich of that name the third, Count Palatine by [ye] Rhein, one of the electours of the holy Empire, and Duke in Bauire: wherein constantlie and meekelie he departed out of this world the 26. of October in the yere of our Lord God 1576. Taken word for word out of his last will and testament. Whereunto is added the Lantgraue his answere to the French King</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1620-07-01</title>
                  <author>Friedrich III, Elector Palatine, 1515-1576.</author>
                  <author>Johann Casimir, Pfalzgraf bei Rhein, 1543-1592.</author>
                  <author>Wilhelm IV, Landgrave of Hesse, 1532-1592.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christopher Barkar,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1577.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a preface by John Casimir, Count Palatine, and a letter from William IV of Hesse Cassel to Henry III of France--STC.</note>
                  <note>"The answere of the most famous and excellent Prince William Lantgraue of Hessen" has caption title on E4v.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf blank?.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Creeds --  Protestant --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16513:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16513:1"/>
            <p>A CHRISTIAN CONFESSION <hi>of the late moste noble and</hi> mightie Prince, Friderich of that <hi>name the third, Count</hi> Palatine <hi>by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> Rhein, <hi>one of the Electours of the holy Empire, and Duke in Bauire: wherein conſtantlie and meekelie he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of this world the</hi> 26. <hi>of October in the yere of our Lord God</hi> 1576. <hi>Taken word for word out of his laſt will and teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is added the Lantgraue his anſwere to the French King.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Petri. 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Be alwayes readie to giue anſwere to euerie man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Roman. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If a man beleue Chriſt Ieſus with his heart, he ſhalbe righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: If a man confeſſe him with his mouth, he ſhalbe ſaued.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Whoſoeuer ſhall confeſſe me before men, him will I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge before my Father which is in heauen: But whoſoeuer ſhal denie me before men, him alſo will I denie before my Father which is in heauen.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Chriſtopher Barkar. ANNO. 1577.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:16513:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16513:2"/>
            <head>Iohn Caſimire by the grace of God Count Palatine by the Rhein, Duke in Bauire &amp;c. and appointed Lieutenant Generall of the ſaid Palatinate <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Rhein, ſendeth greeting.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the highe and mightie prince, &amp; our entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie beloued Lorde and father, Friderich late Paltzgraue by the Rhein, and Elector of the holie empire, of worthie memorie, in the whole time of his gouernement, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the yere of our lord god 1566 at the time of the diet holden at Auguſta, where he was preſent about the confeſsion of his chriſtian faith: and alſo in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme and booke of the reformation and orders of the churches in his dominions heretofore publiſhed, hath ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared &amp; witneſſed to the whole world, that neither he him ſelfe held or mainteined, nor in his landes and dominions had ſuffered to be ſet forth and publiſhed, anie other kinde of religion then that which was in all partes agreeable vnto the doctrine of the holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical and apoſtolical ſcriptures, &amp; beſides
<pb facs="tcp:16513:3"/>
conformable with the confeſsion of Auguſta and apologie thereof, as the ſame was allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed of by the Princes &amp; Eſtates aſſembled at Nawmburg: yet ſithe the time of the departure of our ſaid lord and father out of this vale of miſerie, we haue partly our ſelues with our own eares heard, and partly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode from other places to our great grief, that it hath bene giuen out by ſome (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though vntruelie) that our ſaid father before his death ſhould haue bene remoued from his former confeſsion, as though aforetimes he had proceeded to farre in ſuch matters. And albeit wee for our owne part, ſith the time that by the grace of God we were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of Poperie, haue alwayes taken and founde his ſaid Confeſsion to be no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then Chriſtian, &amp; grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible word of God, and eſpecially at the time of the ſaid dyet of Auguſta, where we atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon our ſaid father, and by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t exhibited the bookes of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Bible and Confeſsion of Auguſta before the Electours and other Princes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire then preſent, and the Commiſsioners &amp; Ambaſſadours of thoſe which were abſent. Out of which in our ſaid fathers behalf we deſired, that an other and better confeſsion
<pb facs="tcp:16513:3"/>
might bee ſhewed and taught vnto him: where ſeeing none of them brought any thing at al againſt our ſaid fathers confeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wee were at that time the more confirmed therein: And ſince according to the ſame haue not onely with heart and mouth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, but alſo being accompanied with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers noble men, &amp; other vertuous &amp; honeſt perſones fearing God, haue at two ſeueral times ſufficiently in the face of the whole worlde witneſſed our zeale therein. And yet in like ſort (as we haue bene enformed) it hath bene imputed vnto vs, that if we were not wholy departed &amp; remoued from our fathers ſaid Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſsion yet at the leſt we were become ſomewhat leſſe earneſt then before.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe ſeeing our ſaid Lord and father in the abſence of the noble &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Prince, Ludouick Palzgraue by the Rhein, now Electour of the holie Empire, our wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued Lord and brother, about the ſpace of one moneth before his departure called and ſent for vs in this place vnto him, where we remained with him ſtill vntill his ende, in which time we vnderſtoode from himſelfe that not onely the aboue mentioned Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion heretofore publiſhed was with his owne hands made, but alſo that he had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:16513:4"/>
the ſame to be written and inſerted in his laſt will and teſtament. And further are witneſſes that we haue both heard &amp; ſeene, that vntil his laſt breath he with good reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance and great conſtancie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued in the profeſsion of the ſame, and ſo bleſſedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted in our Lord Chriſt Ieſus. And where as afterwards our ſaid welbeloued brother comming hither, and with common co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent opening the ſaid will and teſtament, which in the meane time remained not onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched by anie perſon, but alſo kept vnder the handes and ſeales of good and ſufficient witneſſes, and further was in euerie leafe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed with our ſaid fathers owne hande: we not onely founde therein contained his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentioned Confeſsion, but alſo that we his children appointed executours of his ſaid laſt will, vpon paine of the auoiding of Gods diſpleaſure, anger and curſe, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and worldly puniſhment, by vertue and power of Gods immutable precept of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience due vnto him, were commanded and enioyned both to mainteine our ſaid fathers confeſsion, and alſo to do our endeuours for the planting and ſpreading of it further. For which cauſe with a good conſcience (as we truſt) and alſo without any diſcredit or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice
<pb facs="tcp:16513:4"/>
to our fathers ſaid will, and for diuers other weightie and neceſſarie cauſes, wee could not any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger forbeare for knowledge of the truth, &amp; anſwering of ſuch reportes as haue bene vntruely bruted and ſpred abroad to the contrarie, openly to giue herewith a true teſtimonie of the ſaide matter, cauſing the ſaid Confeſsion as it was word for word written and inſerted in our fathers ſaid te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, to be publiſhed and printed: To the intent that the duetiful accompliſhment and fulfilling of his ſaid laſt and deare will, which is not onely committed to the charge of the Electour our ſaid lord &amp; brother (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though to him chiefly) but alſo to his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, Counſellours, officers, and eſpecially to the vniuerſitie here, the Schole, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, &amp; alſo to the whole poſteritie, &amp; euery man in particular (as is expreſſely conteined in the ſaid teſtament) might be knowen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them and they thereby vnderſtande their duetie what they haue to do: and further e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie perſon whatſoeuer, be thereby aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perſwaded in his conſcience, that our ſayd lord and father, in no other confeſsion nor in any erronious condemned opinion, but in a moſt Chriſtian confeſsion and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of the infallible and inuincible truth
<pb facs="tcp:16513:5"/>
of our common true and auncient Chriſtian faith, departed moſt godlie out of this vale of miſerie into euerlaſting ioye and quietnes. By which confeſsion as grounded vpon the right rocke Chriſt Ieſus our Lord and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and his moſt godlie worde, the right toucheſtone, we alſo through the helpe and aſsiſtance of almightie God, minde to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere and continue vnto our laſt ende: and beſeche the almightie that he will not onely gratiouſly preſerue vs and all our fellowe members in Chriſt Ieſus, from all contrarie errours and deprauations, which by vnquiet and contentious perſons and members are moued in matters of religion and brought into the Church, but alſo mainteine &amp; keepe in vs his knowen veritie, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort &amp; ſtrengthen vs in all troubles and tentations, and of his goodnes once in theſe latter daies open the eyes and hearts of all Chriſtian people, that we may haue a regarde not vnto traditions of men or priuate affections, but only to his moſt godly worde as the trueſt and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt line &amp; direction of our conſciences and faithes, and graunt vnto vs all grace, that brotherlie, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and due charitie may take place and dwell among vs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="quotations">
            <pb facs="tcp:16513:5"/>
            <head>Theſe ſentences &amp; words following were diſtinctly ſpoken by the ſaid prince Electour, being of good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; memorie, not long before his death, after he had declared that hee perſiſted conſtant in his ſaid confeſſion which followeth.</head>
            <p>Firſt the ſaying of <bibl>S. Paul, <hi>1.</hi> Timoth. <hi>1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>This is a moſt true and aſſured ſaying, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy by all meanes to be embraced, that Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to ſaue ſinners, of whom I am the chiefeſt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The ſecond ſaying to them which ſtoode by.</p>
            <q>
               <p>I haue liued lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g inough for you, I muſt alſo once liue for my ſelfe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The third.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The gracious Lorde call me when it ſhall pleaſe him. I haue a ioyfull &amp; free conſcience in the Lord Ieſus, whome I haue ſerued with all my heart, and render thankes vnto him that I haue liued ſo long, that in the churches and ſchooles vnder my domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and charge, the people haue bene directed &amp; taught from traditions of men to beleeue in him alone.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The fourth. <bibl>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Timoth. <hi>4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>I haue fought a good fight I haue finiſhed my courſe, I haue kept the faith: from henceforth is layed vp for me the crowne of righteouſnes.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="confession">
            <pb facs="tcp:16513:6"/>
            <head>Here foloweth the ſaid chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian confeſsion.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>In the name of the holie &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuided Trinity of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Sonne, &amp; the holy Ghoſt</head>
            <p>WE Friderich by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God Count Palatine by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Rhein, one of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Romaine Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, Duke in <hi>Bauaria</hi> &amp;c. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and make knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by theſe our letters. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>¶Firſt whereas we haue bene before all thinges Chriſtianlie taught and reſolued out of gods worde, that both euerlaſting and perpetuall, and alſo the worldlie and temporall proſperitie, peace, quietnes, concorde, and good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of all gouernements, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, countryes, &amp; people, &amp; aſwell of ſuch perſons as are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained heades &amp; magiſtrates, as
<pb facs="tcp:16513:6"/>
other inferiour members &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: haue their beginning, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and enriching, and are moſt aſſuredly mainteined and preſerued by this onely meanes when they ſhall ſet before their eyes and ſeeke to aduance god &amp; his holie worde, and according to the ſame, directe all their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires and cauſes in this life, as by a moſt true and infallible line: which thing alſo the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, although they had no true vnderſtanding of god, yet by the light of nature ingraffed in them ſawe and confeſſed after a ſorte: and from thence at the firſt theſe declarations and making of laſt wils (which men commonly call teſtamentes) tooke their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings: But eſpecially among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde fathers, patriarkes &amp; other religious perſons, they ſeeme to haue bene chieflieſt made to this
<pb facs="tcp:16513:7"/>
ende, for that they woulde leaue after them vnto their children, heires and ſucceſſours, a certaine token and witneſſe, whereby not only their ſaid ſucceſſours might aſſuredly vnderſtand what reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and faith their forefathers were of, which they had receiued out of gods worde by open teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and wherin they had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued holilye and vprightely, and were gratiouſly mainteined, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and protected by almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie god, and in the ende ſo died: but alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their ſucceſſors might haue more cauſe to be moued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> like bondes and duetie to folowe the chriſtian footſteppes of their predeceſſoures, and to imitate their examples, and according to the ſame, to rule and mainetaine the people and countreys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge, (if they did looke for and deſired to enioye
<pb facs="tcp:16513:7"/>
ſuch euerlaſting and worldelie bleſsinges of almightie God, as had bene beſtowed vpon their fathers: which thing appeareth by the laſt wordes vſed by ſome of the patriarches &amp; good King Dauid him ſelfe where he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to his ſonne Salomon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſorte:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Reg. 2.</note>
                  <hi>Be of good comforte and ſhewe thy ſelfe a man: And attende or take heede vnto the charge of the Lorde thy God, that thou walke before him in his wayes, and keepe his precepts, commaundements, iudgements, and teſtimonies, as it is written in the lawe of Moyſes, that thou maiſt proſper in all that thou doeſt, and whereunto ſoeuer thou turneſt thy ſelfe, that the Lord may confirme his word that he hath ſpoken ouer me and ſaid: If thy children ſhal take heede to their wayes, that they walke before me in trueth, and with all their hearts, and with all their ſoules, there ſhall not at anie time a man be wanting from my bodie to ſit vpon the throne of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>So alſo in like ſort as a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian prince, fearing and louing god, and hauing in the making of our laſt wilmore regard in our
<pb facs="tcp:16513:8"/>
heart to euerlaſting and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal things, then to worldly and temporall matters, which periſh and folowe &amp; depende of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, we haue thought good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honor of almighty god, diſcharge and comforte of our conſcience, and for an vnfeined declaration to our louing and deare ſonnes, heyres and ſucceſſoures, &amp; whole poſteritie, and alſo of all our true and faithful ſubiectes, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie other whatſoeuer, to whom it may appertaine: in this our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlie diſpoſition, teſtament and laſt will, to make an open &amp; true declaration of our faith, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one may haue certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, whereto we haue bene the rather induced for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in theſe latter dayes diuers &amp; ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie errours and debates in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of religion haue bene mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by vnquiet and contentious
<pb facs="tcp:16513:8"/>
perſons, wherewith both wee &amp; others in the time of our gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment haue bene much troubled, and ſome ſectes &amp; factions haue bene raiſed in the church by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain perſons going about to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade ſimple men, as though wee were priuie and conſenting to their erronious opinions. And to the intent that it do not onely appeare that the ſame our confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is only grounded &amp; built vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true rocke Chriſt Ieſus our Lord &amp; ſauiour, &amp; his only word: but alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therewith our deare children may be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted to perſiſt ſtedfaſtly in ſuch our chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confeſsion, &amp; for no te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or troubleſome ſtorme what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> might happen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie (wherof god be tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto by his almighty help &amp; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of our gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t we haue both felt and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb facs="tcp:16513:9"/>
many) turned backe or made faynte hearted, fearefull or negligent in their callings, and ſetting forth of the ſaid trew and chriſtian religion: Euen as wee for our own perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as heretofore) ſo notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding minde to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue by the ſaid knowen and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed trueth, through the grace of the moſt higheſt, vntill our laſt ende.</p>
            <p>And ſo firſt and in generall wee confeſſe with an vnfained &amp; aſſured heart, that we ſtedfaſtly beleeue whatſoeuer is reuealed, contained, taught, witneſſed, and grounded in the holye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall and apoſtolicall ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and doctrine in the righte, trewe, chriſtian and vncorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnderſtanding, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſame: in ſuch ſorte as the churche in the time of the Apoſtles did comprehende the
<pb facs="tcp:16513:9"/>
principall poyntes of chriſtian doctrine in our chriſtian creede commonly called <hi>Symbolum apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolorum,</hi> and as afterwarde in the confeſsion of the counſel of <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer apoſtolicall faithe was tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expounded and declared.</p>
            <p>This is the chiefe foundation, wherevpon we and all other true beleeuers in Chriſte, which eyther haue bene before vs, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently are, or ſhall come hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ought to build our faith. And through this we alſo hope to bee ſaued according to the ſaying of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his <hi>Symbolo:</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wilbe ſaued, muſt before al things holde the true chriſtian faith.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the confeſsion and declaration of the chriſtian faith which in our time and namely in the yeere of our lorde god 1530.
<pb facs="tcp:16513:10"/>
was openly preſented at Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta to the Emperour Charles of that name the fifte, with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie thereto annexed, was gathered out of the ſaide prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and apoſtolicall doctrine &amp; aboue named creedes or confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as a ſummarie of them (as the time then ſuffred) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon grounded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues as vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the chiefeſt and vnfallibleſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, the onely, certaine, and ſtedfaſte line, whereby they ought to bee directed: For this cauſe wee alſo ſyth the time that wee came to the knowledge of Gods trueth, haue receiued and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other Electors and Princes beeing addicted thereto, wee alſo for the maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of Chriſtian vnitye and peace, in the righte and true vnderſtanding and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſame, and with this
<pb facs="tcp:16513:10"/>
declaration, did ſet our hande &amp; Seale thereto:</p>
            <p>And according to this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the preachers and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to inſtructe in our landes and dominions, as wee yet alſo confeſſe and acknowledge the ſame both of the ſaide confeſſion, and of al other writings that are agreeing and conformable with the godlie, prophetical &amp; apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical ſcriptures:</p>
            <p>As wee eſpecially take the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thechiſme which wee heretofore haue cauſed to bee printed and publiſhed, and alſo the booke of the reformation and orders of our churches, wherein all the queſtions of chriſtian doctrine are diſtinctlye, orderlye and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligiblye conteyned and alſo in ſome parte more amplye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planed.</p>
            <p>But for the more declaration
<pb facs="tcp:16513:11"/>
of our minde and meaning, and to the intent our deare children, the whole poſteritye and euerye particular perſonne maye (as it were in a briefe ſumme or col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection) vnderſtande what wee particularlye beleeue and holde in all and euerye of the articles of the chriſtian faithe, and no man after our deathe maye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame vs with anye erronious opinions and ſectes, as it is the cuſtome and propertye of manie vnquiet perſons, in theſe dayes of the euill worlde, and for the ſatisfying of them which vnderſtande and interprete the ſaid confeſsion of Auguſta and the Apologye thereof in ſome poyntes after another ſenſe and meaning, then the letter and true vnderſtanding can beare, follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the direction of Goddes worde whereto it referreth it
<pb facs="tcp:16513:11"/>
ſelf as to the chiefeſt foundation: wee beleeue, holde and confeſſe from the bottome of our heart, the articles of our olde trew and knowen Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith in maner as foloweth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Beleeue in God the father almightie maker of heauen and earth: and in Ieſu Chriſt his onely Sonne our lord: who was conceiued by the holye Ghoſt, borne of the virgin Marye: ſuffred paſſion vnder Pontius Pilate, was crucified, dead, buried, and deſcended into hell. He roſe againe the third daye from death: he aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth on the right hande of God the father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie. from thence hee will come to iudge the quicke and the dead. I beleeue in the holie Ghoſt: the holy church vniuerſall, the communion of Saints, the forgiuenes of ſinnes: the riſing againe of the bodies: and life euerlaſting.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>That is:</p>
            <p>We beleeue and confeſſe, that the eternal father of our lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt made heauen and earth and all that therein is of nothing, and alſo yet conſerueth and gouerneth the ſame by his
<pb facs="tcp:16513:12"/>
eternall wiſedome and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. And that not for our own deſertes or worthineſſe, but of meere grace and mercie and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his godly prouidence, for his onely begotten and deare ſonne Chriſt Ieſus ſake: he alſo is our God and Father, vppon whome we haue ſo ſet and repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our confidence, that we dout not but that he will prouide for vs all thinges neceſſarie for our bodies and ſoules hereafter, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he hath done heretofore. And as hitherto he hath turned to our beſt and profite, all ſuch euils as the deuil and the world haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted againſt vs, euen ſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after he wilbe no leſſe gracious and mercifull vnto vs, ſeeing hee is able to do it as an almightie God, &amp; wil alſo doe it as a louing Father.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16513:12"/>Secondlye wee beleeue and confeſſe, that Ieſus Chriſte the ſonne of the almightie God, from the beginning begotten of the Father, is one and the ſame GOD with the Father and the holye Ghoſt, and at the time appointed (as it was determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the eternall wiſedome of God) was conceaued by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſte, in the wombe of the moſt pure and alwayes virgin Marye: tooke vppon him our fleſhe, was borne into the world, To this ende, that hee beeing our King and highe Prieſte (for which cauſe he is called Chriſt) might be our Mediatour and brother, receiue vs to grace, and as a true Ieſus and Sauiour, reconcile vs to his heauenlye Father. We alſo beleeue that for that cauſe hee ſuffered a moſte ſhamefull deathe vnder
<pb facs="tcp:16513:13"/>
Pontius Pilate the Iudge, to the intent he might redeeme and deliuer vs from euerlaſtinge death wherin we otherwiſe were and muſt haue perpetually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained: and to deliuer and loſs vs from the curſe which by the ſinne and fall of our firſt fathers Adam and Eue, was rooted in all mankinde.</p>
            <p>We beleeue alſo and confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this Lorde Ieſus Chriſte being made an offering vppon the croſſe is ſo puiſſant and ſtrong, that by the power and ſtrength of the ſame through the working of the holy Ghoſt, our olde man is with him crucified, dead &amp; bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, ſo as the euill concupiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the fleſh ought not anye more beare rule in vs, but rather we ſhould offer vp our ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, as a ſweete ſacrifice of thankeſgiuing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16513:13"/>We beleeue alſo, that hee was buried and therefore vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dead, yea alſo that he deſcended into hell, to the intent that in our greateſt tentations we might aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our ſelues that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, by his vnſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſorowes, pangues and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours which he alſo ſuffered in his ſoule both vpon the croſſe and before, hath deliuered vs from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſorowes and paine of hell. So that from henceforth neither hell nor the deuill ſhal hinder or hurte vs in our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We beleue alſo with our heart, that the third day he roſe again from the dead. And we are certainly perſuaded, firſt that by his reſurrection hee hath ouercome death, to the intent hee might make vs partakers of the righteouſnes, which he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for vs by his bitter paſſion and death. And ſecondly, that we
<pb facs="tcp:16513:14"/>
alſo now by his power ſhould bee reſuſcitated &amp; quickened to new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life. And thirdly, that the reſurrection of Chriſte is a moſt certaine aſſurance vnto vs, that as he is firſt riſen vp againe from death, ſo wee alſo at the laſt daye ſhalbe rayſed vp againe to life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting.</p>
            <p>And further, wee alſo beleeue that Chriſt our Lorde truely and viſiblie with his manifeſted man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode which he had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on him, is aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vp into heauen, &amp; there ſitteth on the right hande of his heauenly Father, that is to ſaye, with heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly and godly maieſtie he ſheweth him ſelfe vnto all the holy Angels and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be a head of his whole Church: and from thence alſo truely and viſiblie (as he aſcended vp) hee ſhall againe come downe in the cloudes in the dominion and maieſtie of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:16513:14"/>
to iudge the liuing and the dead. And yet notwithſtanding wee confeſſe and acknowledge, that albeit our Lord IESUS Chriſt true God and man, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his humane nature is now no more in earth, but in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, yet according to his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, maieſtie, grace and ſpirite, hee neuer departeth from vs. And wee litle eſteeme that which is ſayde by ſome, that both the natures were ſo vnited and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in Chriſte, as though his humane nature were in all places as the diuine is. For ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diuine nature is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, and alwayes to bee found in all places, it followeth neceſſarilie, that it is both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> humane nature, which was aſſumed, &amp; alſo perſonallie vnited to the ſame: euen as the diuine
<pb facs="tcp:16513:15"/>
nature neuer left heauen when Chriſt was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued in the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of the bleſſed virgin. And all this which our Lord Chriſt hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered and done, we beleue and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that it hath bene done for the behoofe and benefit of vs, &amp; that he thereby hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelf vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs as our owne. And beſides the reſt, this comforteth vs moſt that we are aſſured that our fleſh is alreadie in heauen, &amp; that our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus ſendeth down vnto vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his holy ghoſt as a pledge. By the inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; power of whom, we ſeeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinges which are aboue where Chriſt ſitteth on the right hand of God his Father, and not things here vpon earth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, wee beleue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt with God the Father and God the ſonne, is a true, only, and eternall God: &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:16513:15"/>
ſecondly, that he is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs to make vs partakers through a true faith in Chriſt, of al his good giftes and benefites, and further that he is our comforter, and is with vs, and will remaine with vs vntill the ende.</p>
            <p>As touching the vniuerſall Chriſtian Church, we beleue that the ſonne of God hath out of all kinreds and generations of men, choſen a congregation vnto him ſelfe for euerlaſting life, by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt, &amp; his godly word in the vnitie of true faith: which fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world he hath ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, &amp; yet gathereth together, preſerueth &amp; defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, &amp; beleue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are a liuely member ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of and ſo ſhall remaine eternally.</p>
            <p>Of the communion of Saints we beleue and confeſſe that wee with al and euerie true beleuers, as members of our Lord Jeſus
<pb facs="tcp:16513:16"/>
Chriſt, haue a communion and ſocietie in all his treaſures and giftes, and therefore we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that wee are debters of all ſuch giftes, as he hath imparted vnto vs, to beſtowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> willingly and ioyfully to the profit &amp; helpe of others our commembers.</p>
            <p>Wee beleeue and confeſſe alſo, that God the Father for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and ful paiment of Chriſt Ieſus hath forgiuen, and neuer will call to remembrance our ſinnes or ſinful inclinations and affections, wherewith wee haue to fight all the dayes of our life, but rather will giue and impute vnto vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteouſnes of Chriſt Ieſus. So that wee neede not to bee afraid of the iudgement of God.</p>
            <p>Of the reſurrection of the fleſh we beleeue and confeſſe, that not onely our ſoules, when they ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:16513:16"/>
be departed out of our bodies by temporall death, are in the ſame inſtant take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp and receiued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt their head, but alſo that our fleſh ſhalbe in the laſt day vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againe with our ſoules, and made conformable vnto the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious bodie of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Of life euerlaſting, we beleue and confeſſe, that euen as now we feele in our hearts the beginning of an euerlaſting ioy, ſo after this life wee ſhall poſſeſſe an eternall bleſſednes, which neither eie hath ſeene, nor eare heard, nor any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s heart can conceiue. God bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked &amp; praiſed therfore, and thereto helpe vs God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Sonne, and holie Ghoſt, one true and euerlaſting God. Amen.</p>
            <p>And for aſmuch as w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out cauſe we haue bene ſuſpected of many, as though we helde &amp; beleued not in ſuch ſort of the holy and bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:16513:17"/>
Sacraments, as became good Chriſtians, wee haue thought good immediatly after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former Confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our faith to ſet down alſo in writing our plaine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of thoſe pointes.</p>
            <p>We therfore beleue and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe both with our mouth, hearte and penne, that all Sacramentes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of the olde as newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were appointed and ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by God him ſelfe, to this end, that they all ſhould ſignifie and pointe as with a finger vnto the bloudie offering of Chriſt Ieſus once acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed vpon the croſſe, as vndoubtedly all the patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and faithfull fathers in the olde Teſtament herewith onely comforted them ſelues in faith, when they killed their lambes &amp; other beaſtes, that after the ſame ſorte the ſeede of the woman, the Lord Ieſus ſhould be ſlaine, and
<pb facs="tcp:16513:17"/>
make a full ſatiſfaction and pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the ſinnes of the whole worlde. And therefore the holie Sacraments (as many hundred yeres hitherto in the ſcholes hath bene taught to youth and yet is) are onely <hi>Sacrae rei ſymbola, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſibilis gratiae viſibilia ſigna:</hi> that is to ſay, viſible ſignes or ſeales of a holy thing, namely of the grace of God in Chriſt Ieſus, whereby we are aſſured and made certain of that which otherwiſe in Gods worde by God him ſelfe and his holy Prophets &amp; Apoſtles hath bene promiſed vnto vs. And we beleue and holde ſtedfaſtly, that the Lorde God thought chieftieſt vpon the weaknes and infirmitie of mans nature, and (as the only knower and ſearcher of heartes) vnderſtoode how hard it was for the nature of man to beleue the naked worde of God which is
<pb facs="tcp:16513:18"/>
preached and declared in the holy Goſpel. And therefore he would alſo repreſent and ſet before our eyes ſuch things which we daily vſe, and are moſt knowen vnto vs, to quicken, ſtirre vp, &amp; ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our faith, to the intent that thereby wee might giue the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner credit to the worde preached. As the ſame may appeare by this ſimilitude taken from worldly things, namely when wee receiue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an Emperour, King, or other great Prince, a letter or writing, although the ſame be ſubſcribed with the Princes owne hande, yet wee are not ſatiſfied there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, if the ſeale bee not annexed alſo to it. And in caſe the Seale be put thereto, then it contenteth vs, and then we may ſaye, I haue from that Emperour, King, &amp;c. a letter &amp; ſeale, wherein this or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is written and ſignified vnto me.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeake of the vſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:16513:18"/>
Sacraments, we beleue and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that the holy Sacraments of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as the holy Baptiſme and Supper of the Lorde, were ordeined of Chriſte himſelfe, to that ende that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould vſe them, holde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in great reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and not deſpiſe them. For that they are not onely markes whereby we are knowen to be Chriſtians, &amp; of the ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion before God &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant &amp; grace of God, but alſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially &amp; principally are true &amp; aſſured toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; witneſſes of gods grace towardes vs: For which cauſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal haue yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren borne into this worlde, wee ſhould not as ſome do ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be 8. 9. or 10. yeres old, till they be of ſome reaſonable diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and then firſt baptiſe them: But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther much more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort our ſelues with that which our Lord Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:16513:19"/>
ſayd to his diſciples <hi>Mark.</hi> 10. Let litle children come vnto mee: for of ſuch is the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. If then the kingdome of heauen belong vnto yong chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (as it is vndoubtedly true) why ſhould we then doubt that they are not alſo comprehended and concluded in the couenant which God made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and the beleuing fathers hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? And for that cauſe wee ought not by any meanes ſeclude or forcloſe them from the holie baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Of the efficacie and working of the holie Baptiſme, we beleue, that our children, ſeeing (as is before declared) they be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the couenant, when they ſhalbe baptiſed according to the article of our true, olde and vniuerſall faith, and alſo be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes brought vp in the
<pb facs="tcp:16513:19"/>
ſame, they are alſo made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the bloudie death of our Lord and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, and all his benefites which hee hath purchaſed vnto vs by his ſaid death, in ſuch ſorte that they not onely receiue the outwarde ſeale of the holie Sacrament, which is the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall water vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their outward bodies, but like wiſe inwardlie are baptiſed in their ſoules by Chriſte him ſelfe with his bloud which was ſhed, and alſo through the working of the holie Ghoſt regenerated and borne again to be new creatures. For as the elementall water of the holie Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in baptiſme is not Chriſtes bloud, nor the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt it ſelfe, ſo alſo the holie Ghoſt or bloud of Chriſt is not in the Sacrament of the elemental water. And although the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall water according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie
<pb facs="tcp:16513:20"/>
and nature can do no more then outwardly clenſe the bodie, and reacheth not ſo farre as vnto the ſoule, yet the bloud of Chriſt clenſeth the ſoule inwardly to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life. And as the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter doth the one, ſo doth Chriſt the other, as ſaint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt witneſſeth in the third chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſaint <hi>Matthewes</hi> Goſpel: I baptiſe you with water to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance or amendement of life, but he that commeth after me is ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then I am, whoſe ſhoes I am not worthie to carie, he ſhall bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe you with the holie Ghoſt and with fyre. And like vnto this is the ſaying of Saint <hi>Paule</hi> in the tenth Chapiter of his firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that after the ſame ſort the Iſraelites were baptiſed with the cloudes and ſea, as alſo they were fedde with <hi>Manna,</hi> and dronke the water
<pb facs="tcp:16513:20"/>
which proceaded out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rock. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And to ſpeake of the holy &amp; moſt worthy Supper of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, we beleue and confeſſe willingly, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al other Chriſtians, that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt firſt inſtituted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Supper, which he him ſelfe kept with his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. And therefore it ought not to be deſpiſed of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in great eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; reuerence. For the Lord Ieſus for this cauſe ordeined this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation and fruition of bread and wine,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> that thereby we ſhould remember him and declare his death vntill his comming: and after wee haue bene inſtructed &amp; aſſured thereof, both before God and man, acknowledge &amp; praiſe this his great benefit, that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt hath bene deliuered vp to death for vs, and his bloud ſhed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forgiuenes of our ſins:
<pb facs="tcp:16513:21"/>
which if wee ſhall apprehende and take vnto vs with true faith, it wilbe a true &amp; ſpirituall foode and drinke to eternall life, as the viſible bread and wine is foode for the nouriſhing of the corporal bodie: ſeeing we are in Chriſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of him the head, branches of him the vine tree, incorporated into him by his ſpirit, and ſo for his ſake and through him ſhall obteine forgiuenes of our ſinnes, iuſtification and life euerlaſting. Wee beleue alſo that wee at this daye haue no other Supper or Communion then as our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte at his laſt ſupper ordeined and held it with his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and that wee ought not to haue any other, &amp; much leſſe vſe any other, vnles wee would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly offende againſt the commandement and inſtitution of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16513:21"/>Now it can not be denied but muſt be confeſſed of all (that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatelie &amp; malitiouſly ſeeke not to contende) that our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt did not deliuer vnto his diſciples his naturall &amp; then preſent bodye as it was ſitting at the table, &amp; not yet crucified, to be eaten with their corporall mouthes, &amp; much leſſe gaue or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his blood to be drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was yet in his bodie, and not ſhed (as at theſe dayes ſome haue cauſed a great diuiſion in the Church of God teaching that men muſt beleeue, that they muſt eate and drinke in the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bodie and blood of Chriſt with their corporal mouthes, as it was then naturall and preſent at his laſt ſupper: and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will not beleeue and confeſſe this, which without great preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of their conſciences they can
<pb facs="tcp:16513:22"/>
not beleeue, they are called deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of the Sacramentes and great blaſphemers of god) But rather he commanded vs to eate his bodie which was the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing nailed to the croſſe, and drinke his blood which ſhoulde be ſhortely ſhed, euen as the very wordes of Chriſt him ſelfe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientlye giue vs to vnderſtande. And wee doubte not but that his diſciples before at Capernaum were ſufficiently inſtructed &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded what was the meaning and maner of the eating of his bodie and drinking of his blood, ſo that they had not anye occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or cauſe to make the leaſt dout therein: As alſo Peter himſelfe notablie confeſſeth,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note> ſaying: Lord whither ſhould we go, thou haſt the words of euerlaſting life, and we haue beleeued and confeſſed that thou art Chriſt the ſonne of
<pb facs="tcp:16513:22"/>
the liuing god.</p>
            <p>Out of which confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he made not alone for him ſelfe, but in the name of all the twelue Apoſtles, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that hee had vnderſtoode and receiued ſuch ſufficient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction out of this ſermon at Capernaum, that neither he nor the other eleuen had any cauſe to aſke what the lord Ieſus meant by ſuch his ſaid inſtitution.</p>
            <p>And therefore wee beleeue and confeſſe that in the holye ſupper of our Lord IESUS CHRIST, where it ſhalbe kept accordynge to his owne inſtitution, to the faythfull (for whome this Supper or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is onelye ordeyned, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as for his diſciples at the firſte) the trewe offered and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified bodye of Chriſte with
<pb facs="tcp:16513:23"/>
al his heauenly treaſures and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits which he hath purchaſed by his death for his people, ſhalbe giuen and deliuered by Chriſt him ſelfe vnto our hungrie ſoules for foode, &amp; his blood which he hath ſhed for the forgiuenes of ſinnes for our drinke. And ſo litle did the diſtance or eſpace of the time hinder his diſciples at that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, namely, that although his body was not yet offred and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, nor his blood yet ſhed, yet his ſaid diſciples did eate his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry naturall and humane bodye which was borne of the imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate virgin Marie, &amp; ſhould be ſhortely after deliuered vp for them, &amp; did drinke his true blood which ſhortly ſhould be ſhed for them, as though it had bene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vp and ſhed alreadie: So alſo the diſtance of the place hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth not vs and other faithfull
<pb facs="tcp:16513:23"/>
beleeuers, that is, that wee alſo with the holy apoſtles according to the Lordes inſtitution do eate the ſame body of Chriſt &amp; drinke his bloud, although the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus with that his naturall body be now no more vpon earth, but ſitteth in heauen on the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of god his heauenly father, from whence he ſhal come to iudge the liuing and the dead, as the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our Chriſtian faithe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth &amp; declareth vnto vs. And therfore we haue no need of this queſtion, whether with his ſelfe ſame naturall bodie ſenſible vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon earth, (as he was at the laſt ſupper with his diſciples) he can be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with vs in our commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: But it is inough that we vnderſtand out of his word, that he with his ſaid bodie wilbe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther viſible nor inuiſible neither comprehenſible nor incomprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb facs="tcp:16513:24"/>
vpon earth. And neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les he is as the almightie ſonne of God at all times and in al pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with his grace, and holie ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with his, and chieflye in his holye ſupper where hee is bothe our hoſte and foode. And as the miniſter doth diſtribute the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Sacramentes, ſeales, and tokens, that is the bleſſed bread and cuppe of the Lorde, ſo doeth the Lord therewith impart vnto the faithfull him ſelfe for breade and drinke, (not of the worldlie bodie, as the ſignes of wine and bread are otherwiſe trew meate and drinke vnto men) but rather a meat and drinke vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life for their hungrie and thirſtye ſoules, beaten downe and diſmayed by the knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and conſideration of their ſinnes, and of the wrathe of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16513:24"/>Now therefore if this queſtion be made, how Chriſt the Lorde ſeeing he is with his bodie aboue in heauen, and wee here vppon earth, can feede vs with his ſaide bodie: we anſwere with <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> that albeit we be here with our feet vppon earth, yet are we with our head aboue in heauen. And with <hi>S. Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> We are al bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed by one ſpirit into one bodie, and wee are all made to drinke one ſpirite. And in this our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion wee referre and remitte our ſelues to the holie and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Scriptures of the olde and newe Teſtaments and confeſſe herewith frankelye and freelye before the ſighte of Almyghtye God, whome no man can abuſe or deceaue, that we vndoubtedly thinke, that if wee did beleeue or holde otherwiſe of the ſayde holye Sacramentes, wee then
<pb facs="tcp:16513:25"/>
ſhould as much as in vs laye, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow the articles of our old, trew and chriſtian faith, and ſo ſhould not be able to ſtand before the iudgement ſeat of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in the laſt day. For when as in the articles of our vndoubted chriſtian faith wee confeſſe that there is but one only euerlaſting, almightie &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head in three perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which both made, gouerneth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerueth all things: then muſt it needes bee (not as ſome haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out) that the humane nature of our lord Ieſus, but the man Chriſt by his godlie nature, is almightie and in all places working and preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at once. Alſo the onely begotten ſonne of god through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> working of the holye Ghoſt tooke vppon him and retaineth for euer to the great comforte and aſſurance of our ſaluation, a true and vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:16513:25"/>
humane nature like vnto ours in all properties of nature (ſinne only excepted.) And ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doutedly after &amp; before his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, aſſenſion, &amp; glorie at the right hand of his father, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his ſaid humane nature is and was viſible, comprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and at all times in one place preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, according to his good will and pleaſure, as he witneſſeth of himſelfe in the 24 Chapter of the Goſpell after <hi>S. Luke:</hi> This Lord Ieſus Chriſt is our onelye Sauiour, mediatour, hie Prieſt, King, and Prophet, Lorde and head of his congregation. And therfore the miniſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church cannot baptiſe vs with the ſpirit and blood of chriſt, but only with the outwarde elemental water, nor feede and drinke vs with the bodie and blood of Chriſt, but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the viſible bread and wine. And
<pb facs="tcp:16513:26"/>
of his ſpirit bodie &amp; blood, Chriſt him ſelf onely maketh vs parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers by faith to the forgiuenes of our ſinnes and life euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>Yf he truly ſuffred for vs, if he in verye deed were crucified and dead, then in the time of his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his manhood was not in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie &amp; glory like vnto his godhead in all places, in heauen and earth, but ſuffred &amp; died, not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out infirmite: If alſo his dead corpes was truely laide into the graue, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was it not before there nor after his burial was it in all places but there for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time onely.</p>
            <p>If it be true that for our bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite hee deſcended into hell, then was hee not at that time, as yet ſet at the right hand of GOD his Father in his heauenly glory and maieſtie.</p>
            <p>If it bee trewe that out of the graue he roſe vp from death, then
<pb facs="tcp:16513:26"/>
was the ſoule before not in the body, &amp; ſo the ſaid body was not before out of the graue, &amp; alſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards remained not therein.</p>
            <p>If it be true that hee aſcended vp into heauen &amp; ſitteth there as perfect man on the right hand of his Father, then according to his humanitie he was not already a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue before, and alſo after his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion he remained not inuiſible belowe, or in al places preſent, &amp; incomprehenſible: but ſheweth himſelf there viſibly and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſibly in the heauenly habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before the faces and ſight of his holye angels and men. And therefore hee cannot be without horrible idolatry ſaid, to be in the bread of the communion, or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one place els, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſought by our prayers aboue in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; honored &amp; inuocated as only preſent and bodily there.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16513:27"/>If it be true that as hee aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp, he ſhal come down again from heauen in the cloudes, then is hee not alreadie &amp; before inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible belowe. And he ſhall not bee in al places viſible and inuiſible, but viſible in one place, with his humane nature, that is, in the cloudes where he ſhall ſhew him ſelfe as a iudge of the liuing and of the dead.</p>
            <p>He ſendeth alſo his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into the heartes of his electe to aſſemble and gather together vnto him amongeſt the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the worlde vnto the ende, an vniuerſall church or congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which hath the verye ſame and like fellowſhippe with their head Chriſt, to whome he parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipateth all his heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly benefits: And this fellowſhippe or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaints is not wrought
<pb facs="tcp:16513:27"/>
by a viſible or inuiſible entrance of the bodie of Chriſt into our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but by the dwelling and working of the ſpirit of Chriſt in them and in vs. We alſo which come vnto the Supper of the Lorde, ſhall not nor can not haue anye other participation or habitation of CHRIST in vs, then ſuch as all the faithfull had, which from the beginning of the worlde haue bene ſaued, or ſuch as they which cannot come vnto the communion, now haue and ſhall retaine euerlaſtinglye. Yea Chriſt in his holye ſupper wil impart &amp; giue vnto vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of himſelf no otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo farre &amp; in ſuch ſorte, that he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the vſe of the ſaid ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per not onely in this life, but in the life to come, will euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye dwell and remaine with vs. And ſeeing it is aſſured and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
<pb facs="tcp:16513:28"/>
that hee giueth the fruition of him ſelf vnto vs, it is not to be thought that he wil againe inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently departe from vs, as to the great diſhonour of the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God hath bene forged by the papiſtes, but will remaine in and with vs euerlaſtingly.</p>
            <p>If he hath purchaſed vnto vs the forgiuenes of all our ſinnes, through his bitter paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; death vpon the croſſe, in caſe we ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, take, applie and make the ſame proper vnto vs by true faith as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ful ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ranſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our ſinnes, then had he not a nature deified preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in euery place, but a very true humane, viſible, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible bodie, &amp; alſo at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time ſubiect to death, which was (ſin excepted) in al thinges like vnto ours. for otherwiſe we could not be ſaued fromour ſinnes by him. <hi>Hebrewes.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16513:28"/>If our fleſhe ſhall riſe againe from death, &amp; be made partaking of euerlaſting life through Chriſt then muſt our head Chriſt Ieſus haue bene conuerſant here in his trew humane nature, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in his godlie, ſpirituall and inuiſible nature, preſent in euery place: but retaine for euer the liknes and vnitie of his humane nature, which it had and hath with our nature, ſo that we may for euer bee his brethren and members of him, planted and graffed in him, as the braunches in the vine tree, and ſo be and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine alwaies his fleſhe and his bones.</p>
            <p>And laſtlye if the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of CHRIST and of all his giftes and benefites righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and lyfe euerlaſting, was not otherwyſe purchaſed
<pb facs="tcp:16513:29"/>
vnto vs, then by his death vpon the croſſe, and otherwiſe cannot be obteined of vs, but through trewe faith, which the holy ghoſt worketh in our hearts, then it is certaine that neither the vſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Sacraments, nor yet any other inward or outward worke <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, by vertue of a worke done: can make vs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Chriſte or his benefits. But the holye Sacramentes are godlye tokens and ſeales, by which our faithe is ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and they doe directe and leade vs to the onelye offering of Chriſte which hath bene once made vpon the croſſe for vs. And there cannot come vnto vs anye ſuch communion &amp; fellowſhippe with Chriſt when we only heare outwardely the viſible worde or promiſe of the Sacraments, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inwardly we beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word
<pb facs="tcp:16513:29"/>
of the Goſpel, which ſhalbe heard and preached vnto vs. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although the viſible ſignes may be abuſed by the vngodly &amp; wicked to their conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, yet the inuiſible and heauenly giftes and benefits which we apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d onely by our faith, muſt onely be and remaine proper to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>And in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our Chriſtian and true faith, both nowe and at al times, we bequeath our ſoule when it ſhalbe ſeparated from our mortal bodie, to the holie and vndiuided Trinitie, God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Father our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, God the ſonne our redeemer, mediatour, and onely Sauiour, Chriſt Ieſus, God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt our true comforte: humblie beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching from the bottome of our heart our onely redeemer and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt Ieſus, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee would
<pb facs="tcp:16513:30"/>
vouchſafe to holde his gratious, mercifull and ſauing hand ouer vs, encreaſe our faith and graunt vnto vs a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and good ende in perfect ſenſe and memorie: and when wee ſhalbe ſeparated from this earthlie bodie &amp; wofull vale of miſerie, that it would pleaſe him to carie and receiue vs vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euerlaſting reſt, peace, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes, in his fathers kingdome, which he hath promiſed, purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and prepared for vs and all the faithfull, by his bitter death and ſhedding of his moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloud to remaine there in the companie of his Sainctes and all true beleeuers in Chriſte Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
            <p>And as we thinke to bee ſaued by this our former Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and to appeare with a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of Chriſt Ieſus: So
<pb facs="tcp:16513:30"/>
we admoniſh, warne and praye our deare childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, heires and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours in moſt friendly ſort, as a true father, &amp; alſo gratiouſlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſuch our ſubiects as by Gods ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce haue bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs, our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellours, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and eſpeciallie our Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, ſchoole &amp; miniſters, of what dignitie, ſtate or degree ſoeuer they be &amp; their ſucceſſours: we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ordaine, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, &amp; enioyne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; euerie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by vertue of the immutable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almightie God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who ſaid, I know he will giue charge vnto his children &amp; his houſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, that they may keepe the wayes of the Lorde, and doe that which is good and right in his ſight, to the intent the Lord maye bring vpon <hi>Abraham</hi> that which hee promyſed vnto hym. And therefore wee will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande
<pb facs="tcp:16513:31"/>
with the greateſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, charge, &amp; zeale that we can, that they not onely for their own perſons perſiſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant vnto their end by this acknowleged, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and bleſſed truth of the holie Goſpel, and former Chriſtian co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, wherby the horrible dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Poperie in our dayes through the vnſpeakeable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and mercie of almightie God hath bene confounded &amp; throwen downe: And beſides ioyfully and frankely confeſſe the ſame before God and the worlde, &amp; neuer aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienate or withdraw them ſelues from the ſame, to the intent that with vs (as wee heartily deſire) they may bee partakers of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſaluation: But chiefly &amp; principally wee deſire them, as Chriſtian and godlie Princes &amp; magiſtrates, to whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defence and propagatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:16513:31"/>
veritie, is by almightie God him ſelfe verie earneſtly impoſed and commanded as their chiefeſt and higheſt office, that they would w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all diligence haue a due regarde, that the holy and bleſſed Goſpell and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely trueth of God (which is infallible and ſhal not paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way but remaine for euer) may be preached and taught vnto all their ſubiectes &amp; others apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining vnto them, according to the contentes of the Prophetical and Apoſtolical ſcriptures, pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vnfalſified: that through the bleſſing of almightie God the ſame may be ſtil planted, inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited and profeſſed by their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours and poſteritie, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they may be partakers of the rich and gratious promiſe of our Lorde and Sauiour IESUS Chriſt, ſaying, Seeke firſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:16513:32"/>
therof &amp; the reſt ſhall fall or be giuen vnto you: truely &amp; aſſuredly confirming &amp; ſtrengthening them ſelues with the commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; comfort of almightie God, which he gaue to his louing &amp; true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Ioſua</hi> in theſe wordes: Be ſtrong and of a moſt valiant cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, that thou maieſt obſerue &amp; do all things according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, which <hi>Moyſes</hi> my ſeruant hath commaunded thee. Turne not from it neither to the right hand, nor to the left, that thou maieſt proſper and proceade wiſely in all that thou haſt to do. And let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke of the Lawe neuer depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy mouth, but meditate vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it day &amp; night, that thou maieſt do and obſerue al thinges according as it is written therein.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, for as much as both nowe and alwayes it hath ſo come to paſſe, that when Gods worde and holie Sacramentes
<pb facs="tcp:16513:32"/>
haue bene in any place taught &amp; adminiſtred purelie, clerely and without darkenes or falſehoode, and almightie God by his bleſſed worde hath gathered vnto him a Churche, that then immediatlie and forthwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemie of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raging deuil, partlie ſoweth his weedes amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g it, and partly oppoſeth him ſelf &amp; aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his whole forces &amp; might &amp; goeth about by al meanes he can not only to ouerthrow &amp; quench it with his outward power, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by ſtirring vp of diuers diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentions, falſe &amp; erronious opinions, which alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of our gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (as is wel knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto all men) not without ſome dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger haue alſo happened vnto vs, &amp; eſpecially in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſome vnquiet and contentious perſons of mere ambition &amp; ſetled hatred, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they could not publiſh a better
<pb facs="tcp:16513:33"/>
booke of their owne, went about and verie earneſtly laboured to ſlaunder &amp; cauill the <hi>Cathechiſme</hi> and booke of the orders and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of our Church, which we cauſed to be publiſhed, and to bring the ſame into ſuſpicion by ſondrie ſimple and well meaning people. All which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by the helpe and grace of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, whileſt we ſuffered our ſelues not to be caried away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the right line of Gods worde, nor to be made afraide by any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of outward power, but tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly follewed our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and calling, in the end won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully contrarie to all mens ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, with great and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant benefit both worldly &amp; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and many other bleſſings &amp; commodities which happened to our people, which did at length ſubmitte them ſelues obediently
<pb facs="tcp:16513:33"/>
vnto the manifeſt trueth, we out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode &amp; ouercame them all: and out of Gods worde haue ſtopped the mouthes of ſuch as ſo oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſet them ſelues againſt our ſaid Chriſtian <hi>Cathechiſme</hi> &amp; booke of orders, ſo as to our great comfort, the eyes of many haue bene thereby opened, and brought to the right vnderſtanding of our true Chriſtian religion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of pure doctrine.</p>
            <p>We therefore praye, admoniſh and warne our deare childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, alſo our Counſellours, officers, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters &amp; ſubiectes, &amp; eſpecially our Vniuerſitie and Church at <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberg,</hi> that ſeeing the malice, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt and ſubtiltie of the diuell, and ſo the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers of true faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtians, are like euerie daye more and more to encreaſe and waxe greater: They would in conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch imminent
<pb facs="tcp:16513:34"/>
perils haue a more true, diligent and earneſt regarde thereto, not onely to ſet forwarde this good worke, as they minde to auoyde the heauie anger and diſpleaſure of almightie GOD, and his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting and worldlie puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon them, and tender the ſaluation of them ſelues and their poſteritie, but alſo not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them ſelues to bee feared, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned awaye or ſeduced from this knowen and confeſſed trothe, for any contentions alreadie entered into the Churche, feare of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, reſpectes of perſones, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptes and other ſubtilties of this vayne worlde, but rather open their eyes, awake, take heede, &amp; do their beſt endeuours, that in ſuch places of our domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions as gods trothe hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die bene taught and receiued, may there ſtill and conſtantly be retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb facs="tcp:16513:34"/>
kept, and increaſed. And in caſe the ſame hitherto through any empechementes of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked diuell, and other defaultes, ſhall not haue bene perfectly in al places eſtabliſhed, knowen and rooted in our ſaid ſubiectes, that then in ſuch place or places by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace and meanes of almightie God &amp; Chriſt Ieſus, they would procure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame may be broght in, taught &amp; planted, to the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and temporall profit and benefit of our ſaid ſubiectes.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially &amp; for the third point, we will &amp; pray our deare ſonnes, to beware &amp; take heede of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious &amp; vnquiet miniſters in churches &amp; ſcholes, which in theſe times go about to ſtirre vp in mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters of faith &amp; religion, ſondrie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentions, and ſtrifes about words, vſing vnprofitable conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations &amp; cenſures againſt other
<pb facs="tcp:16513:35"/>
Chriſtian Churches &amp; Scholes, which neuertheles agree in the principall foundation and chiefe articles of the Chriſtian faith, and repoſe the ſaluation of their ſoules vpon the onely Sauiour and redeemer Chriſt Ieſus: go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about by ambition and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe zeale, to bring in and erect a pretended iuriſdiction of a holy Ghoſt, and eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as in time of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Poperie, ſeeking both to rule and haue dominion ouer the conſciences of magiſtrates and ſubiectes, and to conſtitute a newe ſupremacie: whereby not onely diuiſions and bitternes of mindes both in temporall and ſpirituall gouernementes haue followed, to the ouerthrowe and ruine of them: But alſo there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by occaſion hath bene giuen to the Pope and his followers, to perſecute our true and Chriſtian
<pb facs="tcp:16513:35"/>
religion with fyre and ſworde, baniſhmentes and other paines and puniſhments: and thereby to eſtabliſh and confirme his own tyrannie the more. As (the more is the pitie) manie examples partly already heretofore happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned euen in our dayes in ſome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours and Princes houſes, &amp; among other ſtraunge nations our neighbours, where the holie Goſpell a long time hath had a ſwaye, and partly of late tyme ſprong vp, might be produced to declare ſufficiently, what miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, calamities and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes haue happened thereby, where unto alſo al Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, Churches and ſcholes, ought to beholde and looke vnto as in a glaſſe. And therefore we would haue them as much as in them ſhall lie, to beware of ſuch daungerous &amp; vnquiet perſones,
<pb facs="tcp:16513:36"/>
enemies of peace and quietnes, and neither ſuffer them ſelues or anie other vnder them to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded or exaſperated by their meanes or diuided among them ſelues: But rather to eſchew and auoide them, and alſo whereas no amendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t can be looked for, to ſuppreſſe them: to the intent that they be not partakers of the deteſtable and horrible perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſhedding of innocent bloud, which both in the Empire of Dutchland and other outlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhe nations haue followed by ſuch vnchriſtian condemnation and cenſures: Euen as we for the moſt part haue in like maner for the aboue reherſed and other Chriſtian and weightie cauſes, agreed, conſented and vnited our ſelues with other Electours and Princes. And hereby notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it is not meant to take
<pb facs="tcp:16513:36"/>
from true and godly miniſters ſuch puniſhmentes and cenſures as appertaine vnto them for the reforming of blaſphemies, and confuting of errours that may happen, according to the word of GOD, with Chriſtian decencie, which is to be eſtabliſhed &amp; vſed not to the ouerthrowing, but for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> edifying of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of Chriſte Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16513:37"/>
            <head>THE ANSWERE OF the moſt famous and excellent Prince William Lantgraue of Heſſen, ſent to the Frenche King, by the Lord of Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier Ambaſſadour from his Maieſtie to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE moſt famous and</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince, William Lantgraue of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> hauing receiued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage ſent him from the Frenche King by the Lord of <hi>Villequier</hi> his Highnes Ambaſſadour, rendreth his Maieſtie moſt hartie tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes for the good will it pleaſeth him to continue towards him: promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that for his part, his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhal alwayes finde his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie forward and readie, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere him with the like: as his Maieſtie may cleerly ſee and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by all his former actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s tending to no other marke, but to the maintenance of that good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which hath
<pb facs="tcp:16513:37"/>
of long time bene betweene the crowne of France and the houſe of <hi>Heſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the chiefeſt matter which the ſaid Sir of <hi>Villequier</hi> had to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with the ſaid Prince the <hi>Lantgraue,</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters name, to wit, that the King had, at the ſute and requeſt of the ſtates aſſembled in his towne of <hi>Bloys,</hi> graunted them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce forward, ſuffer no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of any other religion in his Realme, ſaue of the Catholique, Apoſtolique and Romiſh, his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie is of opinion and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in truthe there is nothing more greatlie to be deſired in this world, then that it would pleaſe our good God of his infinite bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and mercie, that the ſame true Religion, which was once publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and taught at Rome by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> might through his
<pb facs="tcp:16513:38"/>
mercifull ſufferance, be not onely planted, take roote, and be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in the kingdome of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but alſo, as purely kept and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in all partes of the world, as it was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning taught and pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in Rome, as we finde the ſaid Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath left wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſed in his epiſtle written to the <hi>Romaines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is a matter verie well knowen both to the King himſelf and to many other good men, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are profeſſors of the ſelf ſame Romiſhe religion, that (after the Apoſtles time, when the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Biſhop of Rome became ſo ſwollen and puffed vp, that it would needes be a topgallant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Emperours, Kings, and all other Monarches of the world) that Religion which the Apoſtle had planted at Rome, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſo highlie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended their
<pb facs="tcp:16513:38"/>
faith, became through many ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſes, mens tradicions, errours and Idolatries, altogether defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced &amp; falſified. A matter greately complained of, by many good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both of hie calling &amp; others, not onely at this day, but long ſince, and many yeres ago, deſiring no thing ſo much as to ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Chriſt well reformed. But it preuailed not as we maye appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly ſee by al hiſtories. Which thing cauſed our Aunceſtoures and predeceſſoures of moſte wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye memorye, and other good men in other countries, for the quieting of their conſciences, and becauſe GOD did ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely commaunde them to flie from Idolatry, to withdraw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues from the obedience of the Pope of Rome, &amp; of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to make a reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> writings of the holy Apoſtles
<pb facs="tcp:16513:39"/>
and Prophets, becauſe they had no other meanes whereby to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, and being perſwaded as the trueth is, that it is better to obey God then man.</p>
            <p>And it is wel knowen that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and manifold trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, wherwith the kingdome of France hath bene pitifully wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted &amp; brought to a very low ebbe, there could be no better way poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly deuiſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to appeaſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer troubles &amp; to make an end of thoſe grieuous calamities which haue through ſo long continua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce brought the whole kingdome to great extremitie, &amp; almoſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ruyne, then to ſuffer them which haue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>drawen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from the obedience of the Pope for the reaſons before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned, to liue with freedome of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences vnder the free exerciſe of the reformed Religion, according
<pb facs="tcp:16513:39"/>
to that confeſſion which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King his brother that dead is. Accordingly as was in fine accorded, agreed, graunted &amp; by othe promiſed, by his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and his Counſaile, by the Queene his mother, the Princes of his blood, and officers of his crowne, and other noblemen and gentlemen of his priuie counſell, by a perpetual and irreuocable Edict, promiſing that he woulde mainetayne and keepe through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and in all poyntes the peace laſt made &amp; publiſhed in al parts of his Realme, In witnes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and of his good intent &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning therein, he alſo ſent the ſame to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Princes excellencie, &amp; to many other Princes &amp; noblemen of the Empire, by letters &amp; Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſages vſing theſe termes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>That he would keepe this edicte of pacification inuiolably for
<pb facs="tcp:16513:40"/>
euer, as the firſt earneſt penny and pledge of his word giuen to his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, which, he ſaid, he had a care to keepe truly and faithfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But his excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy ſeing his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſo ſodeinly cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, clean contrary to al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed before, &amp; to ſuffer him ſelfe to be ſo eaſely caryed away with a fewe of the ſtates aſſembled at <hi>Bloys,</hi> whoſe billes were not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the charge that was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto them, but as men eaſie to be wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſuffred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be framed to the fantaſie of the aduerſe partie, contrarie to all right and reaſon, as they of the reformed religion doe complaine and laye forthe their griefes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, to reuoke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which hee had before ſo aduiſedly, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo good ground and counſell ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nely proteſted, to wit, that he would ſuffer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> free exerciſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:16513:40"/>
reformed religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for euer, Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his maieſtie hath renewed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former troubles and diſorders of his realme, which were hardly &amp; with great difficultie quenched &amp; appeaſed, coulde not but be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at theſe news, not only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his maieſties honor and reputation, &amp; likewiſe his ſtate, which entred very deeply into his excellency, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering what occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was offred hereby to all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to conceiue of his acti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s otherwiſe then could wel ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to his honor &amp; credit, but alſo for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> regard &amp; deſire he had to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, ſafety &amp; preſeruation of all his ſubiectes in generall. For though diuers &amp; ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge news had bene brought to his excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he could neuer be perſuaded to credit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being of opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rumor had ben ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly deuiſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome grief co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued againſt his maieſty vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:16513:41"/>
ſome prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded purpoſe, to defame his maieſty amongſt the common people.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe the meſſage which his maieſtie ſent by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Lord of <hi>Villequier</hi> grieued his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie verye much, becauſe it agreed wholy with that rumor &amp; report which he had heard before which before that time hee could not in any wiſe perſwade him ſelfe to be true.</p>
            <p>And although his maieſtie bee not bounde to make his excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie an accompt of his doings and actions, and though his ſaid excellencie deſire nothing more, then that the Kinges dealinges may be ſuch as might be iuſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to euery priuat perſon, for the great good will and affection hee beareth to his maieſtie: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, his excellencie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giuen to vnderſtand by the
<pb facs="tcp:16513:41"/>
ſaid lorde of <hi>Villequier</hi> what his will and intent is, his ſaid excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie for the zeale he beareth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſeruation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties honor can do no leſſe but lay forth plainely before him what he thinketh, &amp; in ſinglenes of hearte ſhewe vnto his maieſty w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no leſſe plainenes &amp; vprightnes then he vſeth in al his doings what he is perſuaded is moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient not only for his honor &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſafety of his perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but generally for his whole ſtate, deſiring his maieſty to take it in no worſe part then hee doeth meane it.</p>
            <p>And firſt his excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy can not think, &amp; much leſſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he be perſua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to beleue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hee bee either of honour or of good iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſireth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare &amp; honor of his maieſtie, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of his crowne, would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer counſel him to breake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> edict
<pb facs="tcp:16513:42"/>
of pacification y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was laſt made, and diſanul that which he had ſo ſolemnely ſworne &amp; proteſted to keepe for euer inuiolably &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breach in any point &amp; article whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>For firſt of al in ſo doing he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardeth al his honor &amp; reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; al hope he might haue to grow greater hereafter, in ſo much as there is no orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo pretious &amp; wel beſeeming either kings, prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, or other noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of what degree &amp; qualitie ſoeuer thei be, as to keep their faith &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes inuiolably. As on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> otherſide there is nothing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth more to their diſcredite &amp; diſhonor, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which draweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good willes &amp; peoples hearts fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, or is ſo preiudicious &amp; hurtefull to their greatnes, as to ſpeak one thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in worde, &amp; to doe an other thing in deede. All hiſtoryes both eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall and prophane, all exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb facs="tcp:16513:42"/>
aſwell ancient as moderne teach vs and witneſſe vnto vs, not onely how ſhameful a faulte this is in the ſight of men, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo howe diſpleaſing it is to God himſelf, who hath in former time poured out his iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that haue faulted in the ſame. To which purpoſe his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency cannot but lay before his maieſtie amongſt an infinite no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of others, the example of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungarie, Boheme</hi> and <hi>Polonie,</hi> that dead is, who becauſe he ſuffred him ſelfe to bee perſwaded by the Pope &amp; Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a wicked &amp; foliſh colour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould be eaſily abſolued af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, to breake his promiſſe which he had giuen, not to one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> made profeſsion of Chriſtianity, but to <hi>Amurates</hi> Emperor of the turkes &amp; enemy to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, did by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occaſion not onely leeſe his kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but alſo his life &amp; what els
<pb facs="tcp:16513:43"/>
ſoeuer he had in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, &amp; more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer &amp; beſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, his head was, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great diſhonour &amp; ſhame of all chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dom, caryed throughout al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> townes of Aſia. As his excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hath declared more at large this pitiful hiſtory &amp; certein other to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame effect, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid L. of <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lequier,</hi> being moued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſire he hath to preuente the miſchiefe which is like to enſue, for the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere affection which hee beareth to the weale of France, &amp; only of purpoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might ſerue for a looking glaſſe &amp; exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of others, not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he deſireth in any wiſe that any ſuch inconuenience ſhoulde befall to his maieſtie, which is a thing fartheſt from his thought, as the ſaid lord of <hi>Villequier</hi> can informe him and is well able for the ſufficiencye that is in him to giue his maieſtye a vewe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16513:43"/>Who hath moreouer to wey &amp; conſider diligentlye in him ſelfe what troubles &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniences, yea what bloodſhedde hee is to looke for in his kingdome, and what calamities are like to enſue thereof, as alſo what yſſue maye bee hoped for of thoſe kinde of dealings: for moreouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that it wil bee a very harde matter for his maieſtie, to roote out, not only thoſe that are next of his bloode, but alſo ſo manye thouſand perſons which are all his owne ſubiectes. And deſire nothing more then to employe both their life &amp; goods &amp; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer els they might haue in this world for the ſeruice of his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, it is alſo greatly to be feared, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame men perceiuing nowe what his intent and purpoſe is, &amp; being cleane out of hope for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to come to any reconciliation
<pb facs="tcp:16513:44"/>
or to purchaſe the fauour of their Prince and naturall Lord: And ſeeing them ſelues clean ſhut out of all hope of quietnes hereafter, be not in fine conſtrained for the preſeruation of their liues and goods, to reſort to the laſt &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme remedie, which may be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry preiudicious both to his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and alſo to the whole crown of France.</p>
            <p>And alſo it wil bee very harde and a matter of great difficultye for his maieſtie to kicke againſt the pricke, and to plucke out of the heartes of his ſubiectes by force a knowen and perſwaded trueth, and to ſtoppe the courſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Goſpel which the Lorde will haue ſpredde abroade euery day more and more, yea, though it were ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his maieſtye were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (as happely many men deſire) to root out al his ſubiects which
<pb facs="tcp:16513:44"/>
make profeſſion of the ſame refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med religion, what ſhoulde his maieſtie do otherwiſe therin, but to the great hurte and decaye of his kingdome, diſmember one of his armes, yea the beſt arme hee hath, and ſo weake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelf more and more, and bereue and ſpoile him ſelfe of his owne forces.</p>
            <p>And though ſome perſuade his maieſtie that to haue two diuers Religions in his kingdom is the cauſe of thoſe troubles &amp; diſſeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which fall out there, and in caſe he ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, he ſhal not be able to keepe his ſubiectes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which they owe to their ſuperioures, for proofe whereof, they alleage y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; Electors of Germany, who wil not ſuffer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in their territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exerciſe of any religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaue of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which they profeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding his excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie
<pb facs="tcp:16513:45"/>
doubteth not, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his maieſtie knoweth right wel, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made in the Empire for the matter of religion, there is with in the ſame, free exerciſe of them both permitted, and he knoweth that the ſame order is obſerued in the kingdome of <hi>Polonie.</hi> In like ſort did the Emperour that dead is, of moſt famous memory, and ſo doeth his ſonne the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour that now is, ſuffer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his territories and in manye townes, yea, euen in his court at <hi>Vienna,</hi> free exerciſe of two religions: by meanes whereof was maineteyned in al reſpectes as it is alſo at this daye, verye good peace and concorde in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many. And ſo in like ſort y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of France conſiſting of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; diuers prouinces, is in no reſpect to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to any one prince or elector of Germany, not
<pb facs="tcp:16513:45"/>
only becauſe there is no propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion comparable, but alſo becauſe the ſaid Princes and Electours did neuer make any ſuch ſolemne promiſſe to their ſubiects, as his Maieſtie hath done to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom God hath committed to his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement.</p>
            <p>And therefore, his excellencie praieth his Maieſtie againe, that he would not ſuffer him ſelf to be caried away with this perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the ſufferance of the exerciſe of the reformed religion ſhould be the cauſe of thoſe troubles &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſions, which haue continued to this day in France, for it is no new thing for the Chriſtians and profeſſors of true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed and blamed as authours &amp; cauſes of rebellion and ſedition: for ſo it fared not onely with the holie Prophetes and Apoſtles, but alſo with Ieſus Chriſt him
<pb facs="tcp:16513:46"/>
ſelf, although both hee and they were wrongfully charged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with and againſt all truth. But that it would pleaſe his Maieſtie to beleue and aſſure him ſelfe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that the ſtay and hinderance which ſome go about to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the free courſe of Chriſtian Religion, is the onely cauſe of all the calamities and miſeries that haue fallen out heretofore, &amp; may hereafter in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
            <p>And therefore his excellencie prayeth &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelleth his Maieſt. as earneſtly as he can, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would haue regarde of his honor, of his faith &amp; promes, &amp; of his reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to keepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſafe &amp; vnattainted, &amp; alſo to wey aduiſedly how much the matter importeth him, howe many and great inconueniences depende theron, and neuer ſuffer himſelf to be perſuaded to haue a minde to follow a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaile which
<pb facs="tcp:16513:46"/>
can neuer be put in execution, but it wilbe the vtter vndoing of the ſame, the ſhedding of an infinite deale of bloud, &amp; is alſo directlie contrarie to his faith, promiſe &amp; word of a Prince which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie hath giuen to his ſubiectes, but rather that hee would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine and confirme the edict of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that was laſt publiſhed, in all the pointes and articles of the ſame. And in caſe his Maieſt. were deſirous to make ſome good accorde in the matter of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ſurely were a Princely act and worthy a Chriſtian, he were beſt for the accompliſhing of the ſame, to vſe not the edge of the ſworde, but according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his predeceſſours of worthie memorie, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, <hi>Theodocius,</hi> and others, the ſharpe ſworde of the worde of God, by the meanes of a free and
<pb facs="tcp:16513:47"/>
nationall counſel: for it hath bene proper eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the beginning &amp; at all times for the Churche, and ſo ſhall it continue to the end, that ſeeing the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof hath bene laide by bloud, it ſhall neuer be rooted out by ſheddi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of bloud, but the more it is watered with bloud, the more it ſhall increaſe, &amp; ſtretche more large abroade.</p>
            <p>As for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid L. of <hi>Villequier,</hi> wherein his Maieſtie requeſteth his excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie that he would haue nothing to do with them of the religion, nor miniſter them any aide or fauour againſt him in caſe he ſhould be required to the ſame, his excellencie would that his Maieſtie ſhould witte and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that hitherunto he hath medled with other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s matters as litle as he might, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neuer gaue occaſion either by
<pb facs="tcp:16513:47"/>
waye of counſell or otherwiſe to his ſubiectes to riſe againſt him, and his excellencie hopeth that he ſhall haue occaſion euer hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (ſo that it may ſtande with the ſafenes of his conſcience) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in this good affection and ſingular amitie which he beareth to his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Whom hee prayeth moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie in this behalf to take in good part all that he hath ſaid before, as proceading from a heart that beareth a true affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him, and reſpecteth nothing els but his honour and eſtimation, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his proſperous &amp; quiet ſtate, and to ſhewe him ſelfe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth a King that hath a care to mainteine his honour &amp; reputation with all men, as his excellencie truſteth God wil giue him the grace to do, which ſhall not only tende to the aduancing
<pb facs="tcp:16513:48"/>
of Gods glory, but alſo generally to the whole eſtate and preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both of his perſone and all his ſubiectes, and of his whole Realme.</p>
            <p>And this is all that his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie could anſwere to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which the ſaid Lord of <hi>Villequier</hi> had in charge to deliuer vnto him from his Maieſtie.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen at Caſſel</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 18. <hi>of March.</hi> 1577.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed beneath. <hi>William Lantgraue of Heſſen.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16513:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
